Guide to the Ken Knabb Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ken Knabb papers
1939-2010
GEN MSS 1456
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
52.58
(48 containers) + 1 broadside
Knabb, Ken
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, printed material, photographs, audio visual material, electronic files, and other papers by or relating to Ken Knabb.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Boxes 13: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 43-47 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 48-49 (digital media): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: I. Correspondence, circa 1970s-2010s. II. Writings and publications, circa 1970s-2003. III. Subject files, 1939-2005. IV. Printed material, circa 1960s-2006. V. Posters, circa 1970s. VI. Audiovisual material, 1956-1996. VII. Electronic media, circa 1977-2000s.
Ken Knabb
Ken Knabb is an American writer, translator, and radical theorist known for his translations of Guy Debord and the Situationist International.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Ken Knabb and Didier Lecointre-Dominique Drouet on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2016.
Knabb, Ken
- Correspondence, circa 1970s-2010; Series I; 3.25; (3 containers)
  - Correspondence with foreign groups and individuals, circa 1970s-2010 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains correspondence with: Isaac Cronin, Dan Hammer, Gina Rosenberg, Chris Shutes, Jeanne Smith, Tita Carrion, Robert Cooperstein, notice groups, Jim Brook, Linda Wiens (Annihiland), Jerry Beers, John Lepper, Unru Lee, Twilight In Turkey (Chicago journal), Lorraine Perlman / Black & Red, Nick Brandt / Spontaneous Combustion, John McHale, and Tommy Haruki. Also contains correspondence from: Canada, Latin America, Africa, Hong Kong, Japan, Indonesia, New Zealand, Australia, miscellaneous non-European countries, and England.
  - Correspondence with foreign groups and individuals, circa 1970s-2010 (Box 2)
    Contains correspondence from: Greece, Spain / Portugal, Italy, Germany, Scandinavia, Poland and Eastern Europe, miscellaneous Euroean countries (including Switzerland, Belgium, Netherlands, Austria), and France. Also includes correspondence with: Jean-Francois Labrugere, Christian Camous, Daniel and Francoise Denevert, Joel Cornuault and Nadine Bloch, Center for Research on Social Question - CRQS (regarding split), Andre Trillaud, Jean Pérès, Roger Gregoire and Linda Lanphear, Jean-Pierre Voyer, and Gérard Lambert.
  - Correspondence, articles and reviews, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 3)
    Contains material relating to: Situationist International Anthology, specifically letters requesting permission to reproduce articles, reviews and responses, leftover notes and unused articles, publicity materials, and letters to various publishers regarding attempts to unsuccessfully publish the anthology; Village Voice articles regarding Situationist International, and people influenced by Situationist International; notes, articles and leaflets regarding Guy Debord films, film translations and Alice Debord's Les Princes du Jargon; comments on Bureau of Public Secrets (BPS). Also contains: miscellaneous correspondence, including letters from over 100 United States prisoners.
- Writings and publications, circa 1970s-2003; Series II; 19.67; (15 containers) + 1 broadside
  - Unpublished notes and drafts, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 4)
    Contains: early drafts and notes from "Confessions of a Mild-Mannered Enemy of the State" and "The Joy of Revolution," sources for "The Joy of Revolution," draft designs for the cover of "Public Secrets," reprint and translations of various Ken Knabb publications, notes on diverse topics (including Gary Snyder, religion, the Gulf War, books, radical film, etc.), documents and letters regarding the 1977 break-up of the Notice group, and various other manuscript material.
  - Unpublished notes and drafts, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 5)
    Contains: Notes regarding the 1977 breakup of the Notice group, Notes regarding Ken Knabb's Japan and Hong Kong trip (Fall 1977), including notes and drafts for "A Radical Group in Hong Kong," notes regarding Ken Knabb and Isaac Cronin's 1982 New Orleans trip, and personal notes regarding dreams.
  - Publications, notes and correspondence, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 6)
    Contains: material by Council for the Eruption of the Marvelous (1970); minor leaflets related to the Bureau of Public Secrets (1973-), as well as price lists, publicity materials, order forms, and annoucements of new publications; early texts by Ken Knabb and Ron Rothbart, including "1044" items (circa 1970); notes and drafts regarding Contradiction, an unrealized journal regarding critiques of the New Left movement (circa 1970-1972), including "Movement Critique," "Poverty of Hip Life," "Contradiction Journal" and "Contradiction Texts"; leaflets and pamphlets regarding Point-Blank (after Contradiction); various Bureau of Public Secrets material (1973-). Also contains publications and correspondence from other American Situationist groups.
  - Publications, notes and correspondence, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 7)
    Contains publications and correspondence from American Situationist groups and people, including: Processed World, Columbia Anarchist League (C.A.L.) Press, Against Sleep and Nightmare (A.S.A.N.), John Zerzan, The Last International / Bob Black, Not Bored!, Len Bracken, Fifth Estate, and For Ourselves.
  - Drafts and proofs, circa 2000s (Box 8)
    Contains drafts and proofs of: The Complete Poems of Kenneth Rexroth (circa 2002); Public Secrets: Collected Skirmishes of Ken Knabb; In the Crossfire: Adventures of a Vietnamese Revolutionary; Guy Debord: Complete Cinematic Works (circa 2003); Centre de Recherche sur la Question Sociale / Bureau of Public Secrets (circa 1974).
  - Drafts and proofs, circa 2003 (Box 9)
    Contains drafts and proofs of: Guy Debord: Complete Cinematic Works.
  - Situationist International Anthology, galley proofs, undated (Box 10)
    Contains galley proofs on index cards. Also contains a typescript draft, an Altaquito pamphlet, and a Chicago Review postcard and subscription envelope.
  - Situationist International Anthology, Dave Blake's tapes for "Suppress Religion pamphlet", 1977-03 (Box 11)
    Contains chadless microcomputer tape.
  - Situationist International Anthology, drafts and proofs, circa 1981 (Box 12)
  - Situationist International Anthology, reproductions, circa 1980s (Box 13)
    Contains reproductions of proofs.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Situationist International Anthology, index cards, undated (Box 14)
  - Situationist International Anthology, index cards, undated (Box 15)
  - Situationist International Anthology, offset master negatives, circa 1995-2000s (Box 16 (Oversize))
    Contains offset master negatives, used in the printing process of Situationist International Anthology.
  - Situationist International Anthology, offset master negatives, circa 1995 (Box 17 (Broadside))
    Contains offset master negatives, used in the printing process of Situationist International Anthology. Also contains a photocopy of the proof for Public Secrets.
  - Situationist International Anthology, layouts and proofs, circa 1990s (Box 18 (Oversize))
    Contains: Bureau of Public Secrets buisness card; Bureau of Public Secrets "Evading the Transformation of Reality" and "The War and the Spectacle" print sheets; Situationist International Anthology layout proofs; Situationist International Anthology book cover proofs.
  - Notes, drafts, and correspondence, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 36)
    Contains notes, drafts and correspondence regarding Ken Knabb's publications and translations. Includes Double-Reflection material, Society of Situationism (S.O.S.) material, and Situationist International Anthology material.
- Subject files, 1939-2005; Series III; 14.92; (14 containers)
  - French Songs, undated (Box 19)
    Contains photocopies of the lyrics of French songs.
  - Files and photocopies, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 20)
    Contains files related to: the Gulf War (1990-1991); Engaged Buddhism; "We Don't Want Full Employment (Workless Movement)", Dorothe (Bendon) van Ghent's master thesis on Gertrude Stein, Laura Riding and Kenneth Rexroth (1935); "Kenneth Rexroth: At Large in San Francisco" drafts; "Bureau of Public Secrets" website print-outs, statistics and indexes; recent typed notes; Potlatch, number 1, photocopy (22 June 1954); "The Society of the Spectable," by Guy Debord, uncorrected proof (1990); The Situationist International: The Real Split; Secret Publics: Escarmouches complètes de Ken Knabb, 1970-1997 (1997).
  - Files and photocopies, circa 1980s (Box 21)
    Contains files related to: Débat d'Orientation de l'Ex-Internationale Situationniste; Recordando a Los Clásicos.
  - Kenneth Rexroth material, 1939-2005
    - Rexroth, Kenneth - Camping in the Western Mountains, circa 1939 (Box 19)
      Contains photocopies of the unpublished manual, reproduced from the State University of New York at Buffalo.
    - Documents regarding Kenneth Rexroth, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 22)
      Contains material regarding Gary Snyder, various printed material specifically regarding Kenneth Rexroth, Kenneth Rexroth's correspondence, Morgan Gibson's "Revolutionary Rexroth," various correspondence regarding Kenneth Rexroth's writings, photocopies of interviews, and various material involving Ken Knabb's book "The Relevance of Rexroth," as well as it's translation into French and Spanish.
    - Documents regarding Kenneth Rexroth, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 23)
      Contains various material regarding Kenneth Rexroth, including writings by others on Rexroth, reviews of Kenneth Rexroth, and interviews. Also contains a draft of Ken Knabb's "The Relevance of Rexroth."
    - Kenneth Rexroth t-shirt, circa 2005 (Box 24 (Oversize))
      Contains a t-shirt, produced in Japan, for an international festival celebrating Kenneth Rexroth, and the 100th year of his birth. The t-shirt is orange, has an image of Rexroth. The shirt is dated 22 August 2005.
    - Kenneth Rexroth photostats, circa 1960s (Box 25 (Oversize))
      Contains various photostatic copies of Kenneth Rexroth articles and material.
  - Richard Kempton material, 1960-1989
    - Printed material from the collection of Richard Kempton, 1960-1988 (Box 26)
      Contains books with marginalia, from Richard Kempton's collection. Also contains various bookmarks removed from printed materials.
    - The Sixties: Clippings, with emphasis on Berkeley., circa 1960s-1980s (Box 27)
      Contains a large three-ring binder with 1960s and post-Sixties articles and flyers, from the collection of Richard Kempton.
    - "Heel dit Raderwerk Staat Stil... Als Uw Macht'ge Arm Dat Wil," poster, circa 1960s (Box 28 (Oversize))
      Contains Dutch poster, from the collection of Richard Kempton.
    - Sixties and post-Sixties material, circa 1966-1974 (Box 29)
      Contains various material from the collection of Richard Kempton: The International Times newspaper (1966 November-1968 September); Earth magazine (1971 September); Ramparts magazine (1973 February); a photocopy of "When The New Left Was New," by Stanley Aronowitz; "Making History vs. Making Life: Dilemmas of an American Left," typescript, by Dick Flacks. Also includes a dealer list of Richard Kempton material found within the collection.
    - Berkeley Barb, newspaper, circa 1966-1972 (Box 30)
      Contains incomplete issues from the collection of Richard Kempton.
    - Berkeley Barb, newspaper, 1966-1970 (Box 31)
    - Counter-culture newspapers, circa 1960-1989 (Box 32)
      Contains various incomplete newspapers from the collection of Richard Kempton, concentrating on 1960s and 1970s counter-culture. Includes: San Francisco's Dock of the Bay newspaper (1972); City Miner peridocial (1979); Express newspaper (1989); Counter Catalogue (Spring 1973); The Daily Gater, San Francisco State College newspaper (1967); NYT Super Love newspaper, Dutch (1968); The Organ newspaper (circa 1970s); The Daily Californian, University of California, Berkeley, newspaper (1960-1984); S-B gazette (1968); San Francisco Oracle newspaper (circa 1967); Good Times newspaper (1969); Berkeley Tribe newspaper (circa 1969).
    - Clippings and newspapers, circa 1969 (Box 32)
      Contains various clippings and incomplete newspapers from the collection of Richard Kempton, concentrating on 1960s and 1970s counter-culture. Includes: The San Francisco Chronicle newspaper (1960-1970); Rolling Stone magazine (1968-1973). Also includes The Great Poster Trip: Art Eureka catalog (1968).
- Printed material, circa 1960s-2006; Series IV; 5.42; (7 containers)
  - Situationist International and post-Situationist texts, translations and correspondence, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 33)
    Contains material from French, American and Italian Situationist publications and groups. Includes photocopied correspondence, and material relating to: Veritable Scission, Guy Debord, René Viénet, and Nadine Bloch and Joël Cornuault. Also includes: Viénet, France May 1968: Enragés and Situationists in the Occupations Movement; copies and documents from the Strasbourg scandal; Early English translations of several dozen miscellaneous Situationist International articles; Centre de Recherche sur la Question Sociale (CRQS) material.
  - Situationist International reprints and photocopies, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 34)
    Contains material from French, American and Italian Situationist publications and groups. Includes material relating to: Luc Mercier, Encyclopédie des Nuisances, Mordicus, Alliance pour l'opposition à toutes les nuisances, Interrogations pour la Communaute Humaine, L'Insecurite Sociale, J.F. Lahaeye, Laurent Chaumette, Le Frondeur, Gérard Lambert, Champ Libre, various French publishers, Jean-Pierre Voyer, Internationale Nexialiste, Jimmy Lallement and Joël Guigne, and Le G.R.C.A.
  - Pamphlets, notes, and correspondence, circa 1970s-2012 (Box 35)
    Contains international anarchist and leftist leaflets, pamphlets, and articles, especially from: the United States, Latin America (e.g. Mexico, Brazil and Argentina), Spain, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Greece, Germany and Japan. Also includes clippings, Occupy movement material, American Surrealism material, Spontaneous Combustion, Agentur fur die Selbstaughebung des Proletariats, material regarding a book on Ngo Van, and Secrets Publics.
  - Artforum, magazine, 2006-02 (Box 37)
  - Underground newspapers, circa 1960s-1998 (Box 38)
    Also includes photocopies of "Suggestions Relatives au Legitime Eloge de l'I.S.," by Daniel Denevert, "Big Town, Little Town," by Kenneth Rexroth, and "A Bibliography of North American Situationists Texts."
  - Situationist printed material, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 39)
    Contains two Kenneth Rexroth catalogs, as well as various British tracts.
  - Art catalogs, 1995-2000 (Box 40)
    Contains three art catalogs regarding Danish painter, sculptor, ceramic artist, and author Asger Jorn.
- Posters, circa 1970s; Series V; 4.0; (2 containers)
  - Mechanicals layouts and posters, undated (Box 41 (Oversize))
    Contains: Bureaucratic Comix mechanical; Situationist International Anthology mechanical, poster and broadsides; Public Secrets cartoons; a heavily damaged San Francisco concert poster (7 October 1966), featuring The Paul Butterfield Blues Band, Jefferson Airplane and the Grateful Dead.
  - Internationale Situationniste posters, circa 1970s (Box 42 (Oversize))
    Contains three posters with comic art. Two are French, one is Dutch.
- Audiovisual material, 1956-1996; Series VI; 4.08; (5 containers)
  Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of audiovisual material may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Contains: audio recordings of Lettrist Poetry (from Jean-Isidore Isou's film "Traite du bave de d'eternite"); a radio program about the situationists on "France Culture" (May 1996); Jim Burill: The Driver Who Stole Cargo; End of Prehistory (a program created by Bay Area situationist groups and broadcast on Pacifica Radio KPFA); Ken Knabb's recording of "Madrid meeting" (circa 2001); Ken Knabb's recording of "Hong Kong meeting" (circa 1977); Kenneth Rexroth's autobiography; French Songs vol. I and II; Janice Leber's "That Was the War That Was;" Jean-Pierre Voyer: Introduction a la science de la publicite; Claude Meunier: Une societe peut en cacher aun autre!; Situationist International Anthology from the Royal National Institute for the Blind; Kenneth Rexroth / Lawrence Ferlinghetti With The Cellar Jazz Quintet ‎– Poetry Readings In The Cellar (1957); Kenneth Rexroth ‎– Poetry And Jazz At The Blackhawk (circa 1956); Pour en finir avec le travail Chansons du prolétariat révolutionnaire - Vol: 1 (1974); None Shall Escape, Caribbean Situationist versus Trevor Menroe (circa 1983). Also contains videocassette recordings of: Guy Debord, son art et son temps; Guy Debord's The Society of the Spectacle; La Société du spectacle and Réfutation de tous les jugements; Refutation of All Judgements; René Viénet's Can Dialectics Break Bricks?; Les Filles de Kamare; Gil Wolman's L'Anticoncept; Isaac Cronin's Call It Sleep.
  - Lettrist Poetry, 1995-09; 1 (Box 43)
  - France culture sur Debord, 1996-05-10; 1 (Box 43)
  - France culture, 1996-05-09; 1 (Box 43)
  - S.I. Radio, 1996-05-08; 1 (Box 43)
  - S.I. Radio, 1996-05-07; 1 (Box 43)
  - Access 5 - Twilight of Humanity, 1994; 1 (Box 43)
  - The Driver that Stole Cargo & other music, by Jim Burrill, 1974; 1 (Box 43)
  - End of Prehistory, undated; 1 (Box 43)
  - End of Prehistory II, undated; 1 (Box 43)
  - Madrid Meeting, undated; 1 (Box 43)
  - Hong Kong I, undated; 1 (Box 43)
  - Hong Kong II, undated; 1 (Box 43)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books: Reviews (BC1026), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.02), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.03), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.04), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.05), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.06), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.07), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.08), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.09), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.10), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Kenneth Rexroth on Books (BB1011.11), undated; 1 (Box 44)
  - Claude Meunier, undated; 1 (Box 45)
  - Voyer: Science de la Publicité, undated; 1 (Box 45)
  - "That Was the War That Was", 1991; 1 (Box 45)
  - French Songs, undated; 1 (Box 45)
  - French Songs II, undated; 1 (Box 45)
  - Kenneth Rexroth (1), undated; 1 (Box 45)
  - Kenneth Rexroth (2), undated; 1 (Box 45)
  - Rexroth Autobio - NYC - Buck Fuller - John Reed Club, undated; 1 (Box 45)
  - Rexroth Autobio - WPA, 1978-11-05; 1 (Box 45)
  - Rexroth Autobio - WPA - CP - Andréa, 1978-11-19; 1 (Box 45)
  - Rexroth Autobio - CP in the 1930s, 1978-12-03; 1 (Box 45)
  - Rexroth Autobio - Japanese-Americans / WWII, 1978-12-17; 1 (Box 45)
  - Guy Debord - The Society of the Spectacle, undated; 1 (Box 46)
  - Guy Debord, Son Art et Son Temps, undated; 1 (Box 46)
  - Debord: La Société du spectacle, undated; 1 (Box 46)
  - Refutation of all judgements, by Guy Debord, 1975; 1 (Box 46)
  - Les Filles de Kamare, undated; 1 (Box 46)
  - Viénet - Can Dialectics Break Bricks?, undated; 1 (Box 46)
  - L'Anticoncept, undated; 1 (Box 46)
  - Call It Sleep - Isaac Cronin, 1982; 1 (Box 46)
  - Royal National Institute for the Blind: No. 1-5 (Situationist International Anthology), undated; 6 (Box 46)
  - Royal National Institute for the Blind: No. 6-11 (Situationist International Anthology), undated; 6 (Box 46)
  - Royal National Institute for the Blind: No. 12-17 (Situationist International Anthology), undated; 6 (Box 46)
  - Poetry readings in the Cellar, with the Cellar Jazz Quintet, Kenneth Rexroth and Lawrence Ferlinghetti, 1957; 1 (Box 47 (Record Album Storage))
  - Poetry and Jazz at the Black Hawk, Kenneth Rexroth, circa 1956; 1 (Box 47 (Record Album Storage))
  - Pour En Finir Avec Le Travail: Chansons du Prolétariat Révolutionnaire - Vol. I, 1974; 1 (Box 47 (Record Album Storage))
  - None Shall Escape, Caribbean Situationist Versus Trevor Menroe, circa 1983; 1 (Box 47 (Record Album Storage))
- Electronic material, circa 1977-2000s; Series VII; 1.25; (2 containers)
  Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Closet Box", circa 2000s; 2; 8 (Box 48)
    Contains electronic media labeled: Knabb on Radio Literature; Ken Knabb speaks at City Lights Book, 25 January 2011; Situs and Occupy, Marxist Library, 5 February 2012; Celebrating Kenneth Rexroth collected poetry, San Fransico Public Library, 8 February 2003; Ken Knabb Addresses the S.F. Anarchist Book Fair, 9 April 2011; Can Dialectics Break Bricks? S.I., 1973; In Girum Imus Nocte Et Consumimur Igni, by Guy Debord; Society of the Spectacle, by Guy Debord, 2008; In Girum, 2011.
  - Situationist International Anthology, 9 track tape, circa 1977; 1 (Box 49)
    Contains 1/2 inch (12.7 mm) wide magnetic tape within a protective case. Also includes a data sample, printed on continuous stationery, and taped to the protective case.